[Music]
so john i thought we'd start
kind of giving context about how you and
i met
i was a student at the university of
toronto and i actually never took one of
your classes
but i was a student in your meditation
sessions that you had a lunch break
which was great
and about maybe a year ago you came on
my podcast intellectual explorers
podcast
and then when we had follow-up breakfast
i'm mentioning to you these different
conversational modalities that i've been
experiencing and
engaging in like uh verbal aikido
circling um what is it like
inside dialogue stuff like that and then
you got captured
by that sort of conversation and then we
decided to go on a research
project together um kind of get not only
just
reading the primary material but
actually engaging in the practices
themselves so just kind of curious that
what is your sort of thoughts on this
journey so far that you and i've been
going on
so there was two things there was a
criticism that
jonathan pageau had made of my work a
very good criticism you know that it was
very
for all of my criticism of autodidactism
i wasn't talking very much
about you know collective uh
psychotechnologies
and so shortly after jonathan made and
you know jonathan's criticisms are
always made
um in good faith um but um uh
shortly after he made that criticism you
and i spoke and that's why we're sort of
like ah
and then as i got into doing
the the work with you and started
reading some of the literature and
starting to do some of the practices
with you
um this was starting to gel with
uh ideas that were emerging in a
conversation i was having
uh initially the and and importantly
because it was very provocative it was a
conversation i was having with jordan
hall
and he i was trying to get understand
his notion of coherence
and then he proposed the idea of a
metapsychotechnology
i was thinking that the metapsychotic
knowledge in the ancient world
was dialectic which um
which you know and and and it has all
these dimens and i knew it
and all these dimensions to it and then
i thought oh
so first of all jordan's idea hit me
like you know like that wow that's right
and you know and there's a relationship
between the meta psycho technology for
collective intelligence
and the meta heuristic for individual
wisdom cultivation and
and that was all the relationship
between those was was integral to
um dialectic and so that sort of you
know
really grabbing me and i thought ah what
i want to do after
awakening from the meaning crisis is i
want to start developing a series that
explores that because i thought what we
could do is
let's like let's really understand that
very deeply and then bring it into
dialogue with all of these
emerging modalities and see if we could
you know create what jordan says we need
which is the metaphysical technology
that would coordinate with the meta
heuristic of wisdom
and then of course you know the people
at rebel wisdom start taking up
this this idea you know uh about
collective intelligence and how
important it is and so i just feel like
i don't have any uh any beliefs about
destiny or t loss or anything
but it's like everything was everything
is just sort of really
um you know folding together in this
sort of mutually
um affording fashion and at the same
time i i i
i'm starting to uh you know participate
in more and more of these kinds of
conversations with jordan and with
with guy personally for me it's it's
expanding
in terms of like what's it mean for me
and
my own personal ecology of practices i'm
trying to see how does it work with
things like lectio divina how does it
work with the contemplative practices
how does it work with the moving
practices
because you know a lot of these
modalities bring in embodiment bring in
mindfulness
[Music]
so bring in a new way of trying to even
relate to language
um so it's just been it's just been i
feel really really privileged
and again the timing for me is i want
i'm on sabbatical
so i could just like i could just go
crazy on this it's just been wonderful
just wonderful and like one thing i just
want to like to send you gratitude and
love your way
uh because you know dave and i were
talking about the intellectual dark web
and how some of that that dialogue there
just seems fossilized
people are kind of like attached to
their viewpoints but
seeing you like dialogue with jordan
hall or
guy or in the in-person intellectual
explorers club
i see your insights in the moment and
just those like aha moments that you
have
and i almost see you rewriting your map
live
so i'm curious like uh why do you think
that is for you
oh uh that's a really good question i'm
part of it is
um
well these are different aspects of the
figure of socrates
and the practice that he had um so
it's very a socratic dialogue often
doesn't end
in an argumentative conclusion instead
what's often happened is
you know eporia a kind of profound
insight that challenges people to change
uh to enter into an aspirational project
of transformation
so um i've from the very beginning
i was interested in the connection
between
inference and insight and so i developed
my teaching style and
my way of doing scientific theorizing
in which i really tried to integrate
both insight
and inference together and then as i
developed mindfulness skills brought
those to bear
um and and so i very much
i i like i very much try to get into
something
i think it's often is into a flow state
when i'm
teaching and and and then
that is often best afforded if there's a
more dialogic relationship
with my students and then
that got taken up into and it's being
developed
in in these dialogues i'm having with
people and so
that's really important to me and thank
you for for for what you just said
because
there's sort of a model that's emerging
in my mind um
and it goes to an argument that i've
already been presenting in the series
about the difference between
intelligence and rationality
and that the way you get rationality is
by having intelligence to
to sort of you know recursively applied
to itself
and improve its own application and one
of the hallmarks
of rationality is to care about the
process
as much if nf and at times more than the
product
right it's the opposite of bottom line
thinking right
and so what i'm starting to see
is that and it's very good that we're
starting to create psychotech
and practices for you know
coalescing and accentuating uh
collective intelligence but we need to
bring in
the psychotech that gets that collective
intelligence into what i would call
collective
rationality again i don't mean
rationality doesn't mean logicality et
cetera it's it's a much more
comprehensive notion
so and so moments of insight
are often very much about that when i
see
right where there's there's been like
sort of this going on
dialogue and then there's an insight and
i
i it's like a problem reformulation
right because
you're you're not see the key to insight
isn't
what happens in insight is you're
reformulating the problem you're paying
much more attention to how the problem
is formulated
before you're going for the answer and
so insight is when the dialogue is going
through something like a restructuring
or reformulation
and then there's this awareness of the
process and that's an opportunity
to to intervene for the sake of
cultivating the collective intelligence
into
collective rationality although you know
i mean i'm working hard to try and open
the notion of rationality up to be much
more comprehensive
but i sometimes are now i i now use the
word like
collective wisdom now because i'm that's
that's the sense of rationality
i i'm trying to point towards so insight
for me
is both personally uh optimizing i'm
moving into something like the flow
state but it's also
like and it's tapping into uh the stage
i've internalized socrates
but it's also pointing forward to like
how
how are we gonna how how are we going to
relate to and inhabit
the space of collective intelligence and
reshape it
so that we can start to we can start to
enact
collective wisdom and do what you see in
the platonic dialogues turn that wisdom
on
central and important topics and issues
that concern human beings right
something that
you said that struck me is that you said
the bottom line thinking
and uh you know it seems like uh
what's neutered is the opportunity for
us to gain insight in an intersubjective
dynamic and i wanted to talk to you
about like i it relating with martial
braun's term
yeah yeah um like for myself i work at
dale carnegie
training i'm an instructor there so i
teach interpersonal skills and
when i was younger as massive anxiety
social anxiety so i kind of like
did everything acting classes improv
classes toastmaster i understand
and i discovered a lot of these kind of
like intersubjective
modalities that were more it like sales
negotiation even like pick up artistry
and it seems like in the professional
environment which is sort of like what
they say game a
a lot of people are having these
relationships with each other
and it's like i'm instrumentalizing you
uh
to get something so i'm treating you as
an instrument and i like this
term by uh see right mills i think the
marketing mentality it's not only am i
making you an instrument i'm making
myself an instrument so i can be easily
used by you
and there's a sense like people wearing
a mask there's this existential
loneliness a hunger for something more
uh and this is prevalence of
yeah as an art form now
so i was wondering if you can speak on
that a little bit yeah i mean and from
actually also talked about the uh the
the market personality
right um so yeah a convergence of ideas
here
yeah i mean so if you look at
you know the iet or what from would call
the the having mode the
categorical representation manipulation
control it's oriented around problem
solving
right and this is something i think we
should i'm going to make a point that i
think
we should start refining our discourse
about this practice
um so i'm going to make a proposal to
you i often hear people talking about
the kind of practices
we're doing as being sort of motivated
by curiosity and i propose that we
shouldn't be using that
i propose that we should be thinking
about wonder a lot more
and this is important because socrates
famously said that wisdom begins
in wonder because wonder puts wonder is
a state where you're
what you're doing is you're opening up a
space
so that you're confronting mystery
you're conf
you're calling into question yourself
and your world so that they both can
undergo the restructuring
that you and i were talking about a
moment ago
and wonder can be deepened into awe
which is a powerful
you know has a powerful ability to to
pull people
beyond their egocentrism that's one of
the you know one of the
one of the features of awe is
reliably is it takes people out of the
egocentrism they feel humbled
right they get a sense of you know
i don't mean this majority by being put
in their place and and
and their that that their world view
their world and their self is too small
for the reality that they've confronted
and i see what was happening in plato is
you know you're trying to you're trying
to deepen wonder into awe and
and get that going and that's what i
feel is happening when i'm doing these
modalities
right whereas it's not curious i know
what curiosity's like and you know and
here's a pro you know here's a here's a
gap in the knowledge and i run an
experiment and i try and close it and
you know that and that's important you
know it's how you get
how you deal with ignorance but we're
not trying to solve problems here we're
trying to
uh i think in invoke um our
participation and wonder
so that we actually platform people
going through
a transformative process and so
i think we should in order to break out
of the eye
yet and get into i thou we need to pay
much more careful attention to the terms
and the states
that we're trying to inhabit i think
trying
becoming more familiar with
participatory knowing of
wonder is a way of moving into an i thou
relationship where i'm trying to
confront
that space in which restructuring
of identity both my identity and the
identities in the world is possible so
that
i can fulfill the developmental needs
that are central to the viewing mode
and so i think that's an important thing
we need to start we need to start
i mean that's part of why you and i are
doing what we're doing we need to get
more careful language
and more careful thought uh because
we're i think we should start
thinking about moving beyond the
inception stage
and and the promotion stage of these
modalities to as i said
can we start to integrate them with
good cognitive science and move them
in in a particular direction
there's this term that came up just like
there's wonder phobia in society at
large
it seems like um and you and i were
talking about
like experimenting with these modalities
and even like maybe experimenting
creating new
ones um and there's a sense that there
might be needs to be bridges
that we have to build like the
anti-debates that we're experimenting
here at the international explorers club
for sure
do you have any tuitions about how to go
about that
um yeah i i i think uh
one one of the intuitions is uh
to get people to realize that it is
possible
uh to enter into
see the words are so loaded but to enter
into argumentation
without entering into if you'll allow me
this without entering into dispute
uh uh so what do i mean by that what i
mean by that
is like uh getting people to understand
the difference between opponent
processing and adversarial
processing right and so plato had a term
for this you know there's
philia sophia which is we come together
and we we each recognize we have bias
and then i realized that one of the
things your bias is actually
really good for is pulling me out of
mind and vice versa and so we can fit
together we can do that opponent
processing
and create a logos that has us doing
something we can't do for ourselves
because our biases are trapping us and
making us stuck but if we coordinate
them in the right way
we can actually call each other beyond
our biases
right and so that's a point of
processing and that that's that's a real
possibility for people
in contra in contrast to the mentality
of adversarial processing you know
fight with what plato called philly and
ikea the love of victory
where so it's an adversarial winner take
all crush the opponent
because that attitude actually right
removes the possibility that that is
you i think i and i think that
possibility is very much dependent on us
a kind of opponent processing
the possibility of self-correction again
if people of people can
start to move to that idea that they can
be
right they can be in opponent processing
without being adversaries
um and and so i think that's a very
important thing that's a very important
bridge now what that looks like in terms
of a specific practice i'm not i i don't
know yet i
like i see it happening in individual
uh conversations and dialogue where and
it often happens around when people will
bring this topic up for me they'll bring
it up
and then you can see that they they they
get it and they
they shift because they want to try they
at least want to try it
and i i found it very powerful uh a lot
of those times
so i think that's an important thing
that we've got we have to start
bringing bringing into it and if we
could get people to realize again
all right this sounds so trite right but
if we can get people to realize again
how much
we need each other uh
in this um as opposed to needing to be
right
um that that could be been a beneficial
bridge
right it's like there is a sense that of
debate
fatigue i'm noticing and there's this
term i quite like uh by scott aikens and
robert tully's
uh called the dialectic fallacy where
there's like this gesturing that we're
here to have uh you know a good faith
conversation
but really we're just trying to score
points with our tribe yeah right we're
just trying to win
type of thing and and there's incentives
for why that is of course
uh but there's i think there's an area
to be playful here in
this idea of the anti-debate where you
sort of have this kind of like
confrontational aspect about it but
you're gamifying understanding
to give people a taste of sort of like
an eye that way of relating well yeah
and i think the isla
relating right and bringing in
rationality as i would describe it is
about can we get people
if we get them to understand opponent
processing can we get them back to
valuing the process for its own sake
so i've adopted some practices i do i
try to
you know okay how do i know if i'm
really listening i know if i'm really
listening
if another person triggers an insight in
me
so so it's a marker for me if i if i can
go oh wow
restructuring and that didn't or
originate with me
that so i look for that and i try to
sensitize myself for it and i try to
i try to sort of as much as i can set
things up so people uh will feel
free to sort of be more playful and and
and
possibly afford an insight so i i do
i do something like that also i try to
see
of course not insincerely but where i
can step back
and exemplify self-correction and say oh
that was a mistake or that was imprecise
and where i'm not
trying to again do some sneaky sly
things so i can then trap you into
the conclusion i want you to come to but
because
it's like oh right what i ultimately
want for this is to engage in this kind
of self-correction
this self-organizing self-correction now
you have to be sensitive to
where you're interacting like when i
there's certain arenas
where that confrontation has to be more
uh combative i mean like so when you're
in the scientific arena
like you have to come to conclusions
because for reasons of funding and
publication and blah blah blah blah
and that you know and so you have to
accept that but if we can
if we're not so much pursuing knowledge
if you allow me this distinction but
cultivating wisdom
i think we can like we can shift over to
trying to and i'm not saying that what i
just proposed to you is exhausted this
is stuff i'm just working out right now
but can we give people a list of things
that they can pay attention to that are
markers
that they're oriented to the process and
they're in opponent processing rather
than adversarial combat so can you
explain what opponent processing means
yeah so uh let me give you an
example uh from um
uh your own nervous system and the way
it connects you to the world and helps
you cope and care about the world uh so
this is your autonomic notice it's
self-governing that's what autonomous
means
your autonomic nervous system this is
this part of your system that is
responsible for
regulating your level of arousal not
your sexual arousal
your level of arousal how much metabolic
energy are you expending
right now and the point is there's no
algorithm for that because sometimes you
need to be really or
sometimes and you you can't be canadian
like just sort of middling all the time
or anything like that
so well what what and this is just an
example you can see this in multiple
scales throughout
biology with like within your own uh
within your own uh
physiology but let's do it with the
autonomic nervous system so what you
have is
it's divided into two subsystems there's
a sympathetic system and what it does is
it tries
it's biased it's biased it's trying to
interpret as much of the environment
as it can as as many stimuli as it can
it's indicating that
arousal should be raised the
parasympathetic system is the opposite
it's trying to interpret as much of the
environment as it can it has a
opposite bias as no arousal should be
diminished and then
so they're working sort of opposite to
each other they have opposite biases
but they're conjoined together causally
so as the sympathetic system tries to
ramp up it tries to shut down
right it tries to down regulate the
parasympathetic and vice versa
so what that you got is this constantly
dynamic
moment by moment fine-grained
self-organized recalibration
of right the best interpretation of the
environment and the most appropriate
level of arousal that you should have
couple and it's coupled together
and so that's opponent processing it
would be it would be insane
if like like if the sympathetic nervous
system no
my view is right what i have to do is
kill the parasite you would then die
and the capacity for self-correction and
dynamically and fluidly
count recalibrating on the fly your
level of arousal
uh would would be lost i mean i was in a
conversation this morning and what one
of the people said oh yeah that would be
like cancer like where one set of cells
is now i'm going to win at all costs and
has stepped outside
of you know opponent processing into
adversarial so
if we could if we if we could if we
could mimic
that right interpersonally what's
happening intrapersonally
that's what i that's what i mean by
opponent processing so you and i are
sort of doing circling together on a
regular basis we're not just researching
we're practicing it participant
observation hopefully getting an
enough ethnography out of it right and
unlike
our last circling i've had like insights
and it was powerful
and was interesting because there's both
insights within
so there's there's constitutive insights
that are in so i i've argued elsewhere
with leo ferraro and
adrian harren bennett that flow is a
sort of an in
inside cascade i think i've mentioned to
guy this that i think what's happening
in circling
is you're trying to get a flow state
going in distributed cognition
and what so you get you get constitutive
insights these are insights that sort of
prompt the circling and keep it going
and then there's these meta insights
where you step back right like we do
when we're checking out or reflecting at
the end
and you sort of you get insights about
the process itself you understand the
difference here
between the constitutive insights that
generate the flow and then the meta
insights where you sort of take away and
go
i have an insight about what's going on
there and and in our last circling i had
a pow i had both of those in
it's a very powerful degree so just for
people who
have no idea what circling is and i know
uh david's interview guy
and you can watch videos on it it's
really hard to describe like an elevator
pitch but
what would you say uh circling is for
someone who's not really aware of it
people often use mindfulness but i think
they they use a meditative
analogy which i think isn't as good so
let me try an
analogy here because often if you give
people an analogy and then you you can
specified into
more technical terms so i'm a tai chi
chan player seriously
right and you're always trying to get
this bi-directional awareness going they
talk about like having two eyes
so one is an awareness that's going deep
into your body
and into your mind not into your
thoughts but sort of tasting your mind
what it's what's its temperature
and texture and tempo so you've got
you've got this inner eye
and then you've got an outer eye looking
out at the environment
and then you know the way your left and
right visual fields do stereoscopic
fusion so you get depth perception
what you learn to do in tai chi is
initially you're doing both of these and
you're moving back and forth but
eventually you get that stereoscopic
fusion the inner
and the outer right fuse together and so
you get
you that's part of how you cultivate she
right
and what you get then is uh this
this way in which you get very coupled
simultaneously to your embodiment
and then to the environment and then of
course you move and what you're trying
to do
with the movements is you're trying to
create um flow
because the the point of the movements
is they yin and yang they expand and
contract
and your attention is expanding and
contracting and right and so
all of this is this is very powerful
technology
uh to try and get you into a flow state
and now i think the same thing is
happening in circling but instead of the
movements being
movements of body there are largely
movements of discourse
so what's happening is you know you if
you to get into circling
uh you're you're bringing this inner
awareness a kind of mindfulness
but it is you're trying to get it fused
in this dynamic sense
with an outer awareness of what what's
going on in other people and then you're
trying to make movements
that get that into a collective flow
state
so what happens often in circling is
people they'll
they're they're doing a thing where you
can see that they're trying to
they'll give a little bit more attention
to right what's going on inside
and then a little bit more out and then
they also do the zoom out what's the
whole group
what's the individual and so i i find it
very analogous
uh to the practice of touch you because
you've got the
the zooming out the zooming in and then
you've got the attempt to fuse
the outer awareness and the inner
awareness so they're mutually affording
each other and then this is all being
coordinated
so you're getting something like a
collective flow state
that accesses and i think accentuates
um the the power of distributed
cognition it engenders
collective intelligence right there and
to ground it for people
who might not have experienced it before
uh sometimes it's called the
intersubjective meditative practice
and you get in a circle an actual circle
and then you have these sort of
conversational
uh kind of experiences and they have
these neat little warm-up exercises yeah
we do beforehand right
uh one of them i quite like is called
the imagination game and so we're just
kind of sitting across from each other
and then i'm imagining
something about your reality right now
yeah whether what you're feeling or what
you're thinking
and then i state it and then you confirm
that's true or false yes and then you do
it to me
and then if you do this back and forth
your intuition muscles gets quite strong
yeah you build up what segal called
mindsight and i built a little bit on
that on the idea of
mine site resonance so mindset is your
ability to pick up um
on other people's mental states and so
what human beings
do um is and we're doing it now so
i i start to pick up on your mental
state and then you start to give me cues
often embodied cues like the nod or as i
pick up on you
you right give me cues to help me pick
up more on you and then
what i then do is i tailor my myself to
allow you uh to pick up more on me and
so what starts to happen is i read you
and then that helps me
uh better present myself so you can read
me better and then you're reading me
and then you present and then we
resonate and so a lot of
what what's happening with uh a lot of
the warm-up exercises for circling is
we're trying to create
uh mine site resonance right and um
because if i know your mental state it's
right i i'm much more successful
at restructuring my communication so
you'll get me
and then vice versa we loop right and
there's like like you're saying there's
so much
insights that are flowing in the
sessions that we're having and then
you're dropping some amazing bombs
one of them that happened the last
session uh you had to play on words of
peer
yeah right so if uh you're someone's
peer you have the the capacity to peer
through them
but you're also allowing them to peer
through you yes and so yeah
that that that play so that's the
playfulness that you're
so that was one of the like yeah that
like it was like a constitutive
uh like that really that really helped
me stay in the flow
uh i also i that very same time i had
i had that what i would call a meta you
know
i met an insight because i was coming to
the realization
uh well i had the experience that when
when you're in when you're in
circling people that you get that
salience glow that you're in the flow
state or when people are in psychedelic
experience right and so i asked other
people it's like
it was that the case and you were there
and other people saying yeah yeah
and then there was a report that that's
this is often reported and then
and i thought okay well i know what
psilocybin is doing on the brain it's
getting areas of the brain to talk to
each other
that don't normally talk to each other
and i was one and i
and there's a big there's all the hyper
scanning synchrony studies when people
are doing this interpersonal stuff
the brain starts they start
synchronizing in important ways
so i would you know i i i'm not claiming
this is the case but
this is a really interesting hypothesis
to explore
that what's happening is circling gets
the interpersonal
patterns of connection to be novel and
restructured
and we're and we're communicating in
ways we don't normally do
and then that gets internalized as areas
of the brain
talking and communicating to each other
in ways they don't normally do and then
that feeds back out to
help the restructuring of the
interpersonal and then that feeds back
in
to help the restructuring of the inter
and then you get that loop going and if
you've already got a mine site resonance
going you could see why that would
loop so powerfully right and um like
what comes to mind is this this circling
in particular it's like a
a gym to practice truthfulness and
daniel schmuckenberger had this
interesting distinction between you know
truth versus truthfulness where truth is
like the correspondence theory of truth
your map of reality accurately maps over
to reality so it's like you arrived in a
way
where truthfulness is that process the
ongoing process of mapping
and one's a property and the other uh
the other is an ideal right
and and then this mapping process it
sort of it localizes it in circling to
the immediate moment where your felt
senses your thoughts and whatnot
so i think that's very good i mean but
one of the things i would like
i suppose for our project
i don't i don't want to mess with
circling it is what it is and it has the
values it does
and i want to continue practicing it but
it would be nice if we could
if we could bring like so in tai chi
if if all i'm ever doing is sort of
reflecting on my
right then i can't actually ever like i
couldn't ever spar
right i couldn't actually ever use it in
self-defense
there has to be it what i'm trying to
say is
yes we get all this coordination going
and we come into the present moment but
you have to be able to come into the
present moment so you can do
something there other than find another
present moment that
you like that's what the so if you'll
allow me to play a little bit more with
the with the
with the the tai chi metaphor and this
is what i see happening in socratic doll
like you have all this stuff going
you know socrates will say did you did
you do you believe that right now or did
you just hear somebody say that if you
just heard somebody say it don't say it
tell me what you're feeling or believing
right now like be participatory so
socrates is doing that but he's not
doing it just to keep people in the
present moment
he's keeping him in the present moment
getting this loop that we're talking
about going
so then they can then turn that like
it's like i feel sometimes
it's a worry like you know we've got
we're we're
we're we're building this powerful
machine and then we're just looking look
at how beautifully it runs
look at that what you know let's oil it
some more let's oh and so it's running
better and better
and you have to do that you have to care
about but like what do we want to do
with this
what i want to do with this right and
and is it would be nice like i say if we
could use it
if we could if we could if we could
bootstrap
collective intelligence up into
collective rationality and then we could
turn that powerful self-correcting
insightful
machine of your llama this analogy onto
issues like what is wisdom
what is a good life what is meaning like
the things
that we need to have good discussions
about right now because all of these
things have fallen into impoverishment
and that's one of the things driving the
meaning crisis but we could
like we could re revitalize them in
really powerful ways
and so you and i have sort of a like
to-do list of all these modalities to
check out
so we're engaging in circling right now
we have something of insight dialogue
we have empathy circles restorative
circles by dominic barter
and my read is that all these are
deliciously incomplete
yes you know and we're getting a taste
of them but they're hyper focused on one
thing one's on empathy one's on
connecting
yeah and you mentioned this in uh the
last time you came to the intellectual
explorers club is that
like a call to arms for like
philosophers and scientists but also
artists and entrepreneurs to kind of
play with this and see if we can
discover something new
yeah totally i mean and again um
not to hammer on this point but that's
exactly also what you see in the
socratic
right dialogues socrates oh well he'll
talk to philosophers he'll talk to
parmenides or
but he'll talk he also talks to generals
like he talks to everybody
well i think these issues in one sense
are philosophically profound
i think they are philosophically
profound not in the sense of
academic uh conceptual clarification or
argumentation
i think they're philosophically profound
in the in the ancient sense
in which they concern trying to get an
understanding
right an understanding and
self-knowledge
that can really help people aspire as i
said to
to wisdom and to enhancing meaning in
life and
i think um you know if we're going if
it's going to be
effective it has to help like what
socrates does it has to be able to reach
everybody who wants to be less
self-deceptive
more connected and i i this is a
platonic
conceit on my part i think that deep
down everybody does
want that um and so yeah i think very
much
um we've got it we've got to engineer
this and reverse engineer
uh this so they can do exactly that that
we can
we can say look we need we need
we need this term is so uh
so our terms like well this is what we
need right so many of our terms have
been
emptied and rendered thin but but we we
need a kind of
you know cognitive diversity so that we
can enrich
the ecology of practices as much as
possible so that the evolution
of right the abilities that we're
seeking are
are optimally afforded that's that's
that's what we need we need we need a
lot of people involved
right and it's like it's not just you
and i doing this i just want to like
send out an invitation like use this
conversation as an opportunity just like
everyone who feels resonant about this
kind of adventure that you and i are on
want to join
like come on this experiment yes i think
so
i think so as long as as long as people
bring
with it this attitude of serious play
right uh
you know i i i'm sensitive to the
criticism
um i think alex and alexander bard made
it
in one of the videos that he did with uh
andrew sweeney
i i don't want to try and recreate the
salons of the onshore regime
where people sat around and talked about
the important issues
and problems of the day while doing
nothing
as the french revolution is brewing
right um
that so uh i'm not i'm not making any
accusations i'm i'm saying
that's what i don't want uh what we're
doing to
to become it's got that's it's i i
it's like the meaning crisis and the
meta crisis
i think are urgent they're exigent
they're existentially threatening
both philosophically existentially and
literally existentially threatening
we don't want people who are coming for
to be in a salon we want people instead
who are more like like i said like
what happened around like like you know
socrates
that practice generates stoicism
as a way of life as you know that
eventually reaches to the height
of the roman that the emperor become
like a stoic philosopher
yeah and it's like so i run the stoicism
toronto group here and
and i try to practice dosing as best as
i can and uh
my co-founder daniel uh he views like
we're having a discussion on what does
the stoa mean
right a stol is this place not versus
stoics talk and you know they can
you know just geek out about stoicism
it's a place where anyone can come to
philosophize about what's most important
yes exactly
doesn't matter if you're a roman emperor
or you're a roman slave like marcus
relation epictetus yes
yeah exactly exactly and you know and
then and
and the dialectic also gets taken up
into
in into the church because you when you
see
like how does thomas aquinas write he
writes like a dot
in dialectic form where there's you know
question and answers and back and forth
and
that gets taken up into so these things
have the potential to be fundamentally
uh like capable of fundamentally
restructuring
the the cultural cognitive grammar of
major institutions
like the emperor or like that you know
the pope
right like so that's what i'm hoping
i mean wow that's really hubristic right
but that
that's what i want as a as opposed to
the alternative
of the aristocrats um sitting in the
salons
discussing things endlessly right and
you mentioned the the
meta crisis and how i hold that is that
we're faced as a species with all these
existential risks that are incon
interconnected with each other uh you
know whether it's the
economy or the environment or agi
and coupled with that is our inability
to sense make the is an odd of what's
going on
yes right and and sort of all these sort
of minimatic tribes that uh i've been
tracking through the culture wonderful
term by the way great
thank you for giving us that thank you
um whether it's extinction rebellion
or effective altruism or some of the
reactionary tribes when they talk about
the black pill
it's like they're all looking at the
same reality the same meta crisis but
they're hyper focused on one area
they're not talking to each other right
so this is like what you get in children
according to piaget you have what's
called
um like there's a kind of fixation
so what development often means is
right opening up the number of variables
that you find relevant and salient and
that's not just about that's not
primarily a belief thing
that's a perspectival participatory
thing it's a developmental thing
right opening up the number of variables
and and
and how they're related in order to stop
falling prey to
a certain kind of bias and so i hope i'm
hoping
that what we can do is get people to to
and to that right where no no
there's like the way i was describing it
to you notice there's all these
i'm trying to in the phenomenology i'm
trying to pick out what are all the
dimensions going on in dialectic
right and and how can we how can we
teach people to coordinate them so that
they're like
the kid that goes from centration to the
adult they can pay attention to multiple
variables like
as the child is to the adult the adult
is to the sage that's one of the you
know the ways of understanding wisdom
and that's that's what that's what i'm
really interested in
right and when we were talking last time
i mentioned it seems like to me you're
operating in two intellectual ecologies
right now one in the academic essence
you're doing formal research
and then there's sort of this wild west
of intellectual
i like that too but yeah yeah and in the
wild west is sort of what you and i are
doing this research in the strange
attractor there seems to be this
authentic dialogue
you know this is like the antidote to
the meta crisis yes
well i think i think there's there's i
mean i think there's deep reasons for
that
uh i mean i so what the what the
academic
research is showing is like what what
are the kinds of things that actually
contribute to the people's uh a sense of
meaning
and i so i think what people are
looking for when they're doing this
i i i find the term authenticity
problematic uh but
what people are looking for when they're
looking for i'm gonna use it in the
title of the series but
what people are looking for is as
they're looking for i would argue
they're looking for
a form of discourse that brings in all
of these levels
like all these kinds of knowings so that
underneath the communication there's
communing because
people need to feel a deep connected a
deep connection
right and it also is flow affording if
we're connecting that way other than
just connecting with the content of our
beliefs
and people and what one of the things
that's predictive of how meaningful your
life is
is how often you have flow in it because
you again it's the sense of being really
connected really coupled to how the
world is unfolding
and i think why that's important because
i think well i argue
that the mental fog that is preventing
us
from really getting a grip on
formulating
the metacrisis doing good problem
formulation on the metacrisis as thomas
bjorkman calls it
right is the meaning crisis we're in
we're in scarcity mental
mentality about meaning that reduces
your cognitive flexibility removes the
capacity to flow removes insight
and so it just it just it's like you get
lot you're like the kid you centrate and
you hold on
you get into the eye yet you're trying
to hold and that and then you lose all
the cognitive flexibility
that is necessary for reformulating and
restructuring
how we're going to address the medic
crisis so i think people are coming at i
think this is kind of a a really good
intuition
that if we can't figure out how to get
the self-correcting opponent processing
going on again
so that we can all we can massively you
know restructure
right you know collective intelligence
we're not going to be able to formulate
the problem in a way we need to solve we
have all the data
about like in the sense of the data it's
like you know
you know the nectar cube where you it's
like a diagram and you look at it and
it's like a bought and it
it flips right all the information is
there what changes isn't the information
what changes
is what's salient what what aspects come
forward what aspects received
and where we need we need an aspect
shift on the medic crisis
that's what and i think people have a
sense that it's got to be an
aspect shift coming from collective
intelligence the kind of restructuring
that you and i have been talking about
and just to use the the simple metaphor
of the you know the blind men and the
elephant
yeah we all have our hands on the
elephant but we're not talking to each
other we're yelling at each other
so how do we get into dialogue with each
other but if i if i would have if i were
to understand that i'm in one spot
and i had therefore of a bias this is
again kids kids who are
egocentric and what you have to do as an
adult is learn that
you know you are seeing this room
differently than i am right now and take
that into consideration as i move around
or as i'm talking to you you have to do
something analogous there it's like
well you know i know that i'm biased and
i know you're a boss but one of the
things your bias can do is call me out
of my bios
and we were talking earlier about how
both of us feel kind of pulled
towards this whatever this is um and i
just want to say that i'm incredibly
grateful for being
pulled alongside it with you my friend
oh thank you very much my friend
me too i mean i i mean i i think this
goes back
to something primordial i like
i want to challenge the sort of
individualism this which is different by
the way from individual responsibility
which is
which is uh you know a moral requirement
but the
but the idea that we're all self-made is
ridiculous because what actually made us
so able to kill it i mean look at us
individually we're
we're fragile and kind of badly designed
as animals we don't have good claws
we're not particularly fast we're
standing in this way in which we're
always perpetually falling
exposing our throat and and our vital
organs to predation
well what do we have well what we have
is we can coordinate together sharpen
some sticks and get some dogs and then
we can kill anything on the planet
what made us so powerful was this
ability to tap
into collective intelligence and
coordinate distributed cognition
to solve problems that we can't
individually solve
that's our great ability our adaptive
advantage across
across speciation was our ability to
coordinate together
and create you know distributed
cognition
enact collective intelligence and put
that
to to to achieving goals that are far
out of the reach
of us as individuals there's there's
been recent research
right where they've taken they've taken
rat brains the sounds are welling but
this is happening
and they've actually linked them
together electronically
and the bra the rats are capable of
solving problems that the individual
rats can't solve
and there's been some recent experiments
using chips linking
humans this is how this you know
distributed cognition and the power of
collective intelligence is a real thing
and i think because it was you know our
advantage across
species across speciation in evolution
we are wired to find to seek it out and
to find it inherently valuable
and deeply motivating and deeply
rewarding
and and so like i think like
religions were were masterful at this
like
you know the the body of christ or
ecclesia which means the gathering
they were they were masterful at
gathering people together
you know enacting creating these psycho
technologies rituals
that enact and engage distributed
cognition bring collective intelligence
up and i would go so further
i think that what a lot of the religions
were able to do was to take that
collective intelligence
and bring it into what i'm calling
collective rationality
[Music]
and that so it's powerful for us and it
is what we
need i would argue if we're going to
bring about the restructuring the
fundamental aspect shift we need
if we're going to address the meeting
crisis in such a way that's why i use
the word awakening
not solving it's an aspect shift out of
the meaning crisis out of the way in
which it's fogging our mind
so that we can get to the mental
flexibility the mental wherewithal
so that we can restructure and
reformulate the metacrisis
and then we've been talking about the
sense of urgency with this project as
well
because if we don't figure this out
we're going to kill ourselves i think
there's i think there's
uh i was talking to david the other day
about this i think there's sort of two
senses of urgency
there's that there's the existential
urgency and then there's what i would
call chirotic
urgency there's a kairos here and we've
got we
and kairos is they they that
there's a reason why spirit is the wind
it comes and goes as it will who has
seen the wind neither you nor i
right but you know but what is it when
the trees are bowing down
the wind is passing by or whatever that
famous poem is but the idea
it comes and goes as it will jesus says
that in the gospels too
the kyros is here i think that's but we
can't count
on it staying it will it it's spiritus
it will come and go as it will and if we
don't get the spiritual sensitivity
to pick up on it we'll lose it
so there's also that urgency and the two
urgencies are not
independent of each other they
accelerate and exacerbate each other
if you like that video i'll be using
some of these conversational techniques
we just talked about
this thursday in an exclusive event for
rebel wisdom members
called the psychodynamic is political
the art of memetic mediation
i'll be repurposing some of these
techniques into a very fun and
interactive session
around the theme of memetic mediation
which is all about getting people from
divergent political and philosophical
backgrounds
in conversation with each other check
out the show notes below for details
it's this thursday august 27th at 7 pm
eastern time